<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon the occurrences of the last year from 5 Nov. 1688 to 5 Nov. 1689. Wherein, the happy progress of the late Revolution, and the unhappy progress of affairs since, are considered; the original of the latter discovered, and the proper means for remedy proposed and recommended.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5437A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R188769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789413</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789413</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93860)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2646:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon the occurrences of the last year from 5 Nov. 1688 to 5 Nov. 1689. Wherein, the happy progress of the late Revolution, and the unhappy progress of affairs since, are considered; the original of the latter discovered, and the proper means for remedy proposed and recommended.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata facing p. 1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Congregational Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172724:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON THE OCCURRENCES OF THE LAST YEAR. From 5 <hi>Nov.</hi> 1688. to 5 <hi>Nov.</hi> 1689. WHEREIN, The <hi>Happy</hi> Progreſs of the late <hi>Revolution,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy</hi> Progreſs of <hi>Affairs ſince,</hi> are Conſidered; The Original of the latter diſcovered, and the proper Means for Remedy, Propoſed and Recommended.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. XXVII. 5, 6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Open Rebuke is better than ſecret Love: Faithful are the Wounds of a Friend; but the Kiſſes of an Enemy are deceitful.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:172724:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172724:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THeſe Papers, though in Print, were not Printed for vulgar View; but for the uſe of ſuch as are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concerned in them; and therefore in number proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to that intention. They contain a ſearch into a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Sore, which cannot faithfully be performed without ſome ſmart to the Patient. And in ſuch caſe, they who are wiſe will not rage and ſtorm at the Hand which toucheth them, but conſider that it is but what is neceſſary to prevent greater Miſchief in time. Perhaps the Operation might have been performed more tenderly by others, but more faithfully it could not have been done by any. If any blame it as a Work of too much Officiouſneſs, for one thus to obtrude him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before he be ſent for; it muſt be remembred, that he had ſome concern in, as well as for the Safety of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: And were it not ſo, yet the good <hi>Samaritan</hi> for his good Office in ſupplying the neglect of the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and the <hi>Levite,</hi> was not cenſured, but approved by the Great Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour.</hi> If after all, any one will be troubleſom, he is hereby admoniſhed to be wiſe, and conſider firſt, how he will clear himſelf before the ſupream Judge, who will certainly take Cognizance of the Cauſe, and give Righteous Judgment upon each. For, for his Service it was done, and to him the Succeſs is intirely committed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:172724:3"/>
            <head>The Reader is deſired to ſtrike out,</head>
            <p>IN ſome Copies, <hi>page</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 4. from two notable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Deliverances were, <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>and inſtead thereof, to inſert after the word</hi> November, <hi>l.</hi> 12. And in this, that they were Deliverances from Conſpiracies, of the ſame inveterate Enemies, though at ſo great a diſtance of time, and of quite different Form and Contrivance; the firſt ſecret, under-ground, and in the dark; the other, bare-fac'd, above-board, and viſible to the VVorld. <hi>And to read,</hi> p. 9. l. 31. had not then, p. 11. l. 33. among them, p. 17. l. 26. Predeceſſors of the laſt race, in p. 18. l. 24. Nati. p. 21. l. 21. by any, p. 32. <hi>l.</hi> 2. ſyſtematical. <hi>Other mere literal Faults being left to his own Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172724:3"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON THE OCCURRENCES OF THE LAST YEAR.</head>
            <p>WE are now by the courſe of Time and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, brought to an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited,</hi> Solemn <hi>Anniverſary Commemoration of two great Deliverances</hi> of this Nation, from two notable Conſpiracies of our inveterate Enemies; the one ſecret, and under ground in the dark; the other bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, above-board, and viſible to the World: And the Deliverances were, one of our Anceſtors, but in them of our ſelves, about one Age, that is, 84 years ſince; the other of our own ſelves, commencing in the Princes Arrival, but one year ſince: But both concurring in the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and memorable Day of the <hi>Fifth of November.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God of his Infinite Goodneſs and Wiſdom, was pleaſed, not only to <hi>renew</hi> his Mercies to us; to do it <hi>when,</hi> conſidering the corrupt and vicious State of the Nation, we had great reaſon, rather to fear ſome ſevere Judgment; to do it in ſuch a <hi>Manner,</hi> as might make his Divine Power and Efficacy in it the more apparent; but to do it with ſuch <hi>Circumſtances of Time,</hi> as might mind
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172724:4"/>us alſo of his former Mercies, of his long continued Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and the conſtancy of his Providence over us, the more to endear his Goodneſs to us, and to oblige us the more effectually to himſelf. The <hi>Year,</hi> that of <hi>Eighty Eight,</hi> to mind us of the famous <hi>Eighty Eight,</hi> one Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years before, in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when the Wind and the Sea, by his Divine Direction, fought for us againſt a ſuppoſed Invincible <hi>Armado.</hi> And <hi>the Day</hi> of the PRINCE's Landing determined, by the remarkable Motion of the Wind, under the ſame Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Direction, to the very day of the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> to mind us of the Deliverance in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, upon the ſame day, from one of the moſt Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and Helliſh Conſpiracies that the World hath known. And, certainly they muſt be very dull and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid Souls, who by ſuch <hi>Admonitions</hi> as theſe, are not provoked <hi>to Conſider</hi> with Admiration and raiſed Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>the obſervable Courſe of the Divine Providence,</hi> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving this Nation from ſuch various and continual Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of the Antichriſtian Faction; not only during the long Reign of four and forty Years of that Queen, but <hi>for this full</hi> 130 Years; from her Acceſſion to the Crown, unto this late Revolution.</p>
            <p>As theſe Circumſtances of the Time invite us to <hi>look backward</hi> upon the former courſe of Divine Providence, in the Occurrences of this Nation, ſo there is another Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance in our late Deliverance, which doth no leſs excite our Conſideration, and oblige us to look <hi>forward</hi> upon what hath ſince occurred in the ſpace of this one Year laſt paſt: And that is the eminent and wonderful <hi>Manner of</hi> the Revolution.</p>
            <p>The Deliverance it ſelf was ſo full fraught, with Mercies and Favours from Heaven, that every Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance had ſome ſpecial obliging Favour in it; and this of the manner, more than one. It was no ſmall favour, that it was <hi>effected with ſo much Eaſe</hi> to us, and with the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172724:4"/>Effuſion of ſo little Blood, eſpecially conſidering the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Corruption of the manners of all ſorts of People among us, which not only deſerved, but ſeemed to need and require a Purgation: But the Merciful God, it ſeems, was pleaſed, firſt to try whether there was ſo much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity left among us, as to be wrought upon by his more gentle method of ſo ſurpriſing a Mercy and eminent Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, which if it be not, will certainly aggravate the ſin of the Nation, and in all probability, increaſe and haſten ſome remarkable Judgment upon it.</p>
            <p>But that which I principally intend here, is, that it was carried on <hi>with a high Hand,</hi> like that of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in ſo powerful and eminent a manner, a certain Dread and Terror going before, as makes the Providence of God viſible, his Power known, and gives a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of his ſpecial Preſence (by his Inviſible Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) in it. This is ſuch a ſpecial Favour, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueeth ſuch ſpecial Obligations upon us, as muſt needs highly aggravate the Crime of any unſuitable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, as not only Notorious Ingratitude for an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Benefit, but a kind of contempt, or ſlighting of ſo great a Benefactor to his Face. <hi>Behold, I ſend my Angel before thee, to keep thee in the way, and to bring thee into the place which I have prepared,</hi> Saith God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and then ſubjoyns this Caution: <hi>Beware of him, and obey his Voice, provoke him not: for he will not pardon your Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions; for my Name is in him,</hi> Exod. 23.20, 21. This was our Caſe: And as ſuch an Obligation requires a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Proſpect, Care and Caution for the future, to avoid all Offence againſt it; ſo the powerful and ſucceſsful Progreſs of that Deliverance, muſt needs make the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of thoſe Powers, or but Suſpenſion of ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a Favour, ſoon felt, and eaſie to be perceived, and thereby give a plain Admonition of ſome Offence commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And whether this be not our Caſe, is a matter of great Importance, and requiring our moſt ſerious and deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Conſideration.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:172724:5"/>
            <p>The Deliverance in the Manner and Progreſs of it, was ſo ſurprizing and amazing, as the like is hardly to be met with in any Hiſtory, ſince that of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> and yet it will not be eaſie to determine, which is moſt to be admired, the ſmooth, uninterrupted, proſperous and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Progreſs of it, or the unaccountable <hi>Stop,</hi> which ſeems to have been put to that ſucceſs; and the ſtrange, ſlow, impedited, and unproſperous <hi>Courſe of our Affairs ſince:</hi> How all things did viſibly concur to promote that, but the courſe of our Affairs ſince hath been retarded we know not how! Only this we plainly ſee, all is at a ſtand, or moves ſlowly, like <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Chariots, when their Wheels were off; or as I have heard of a Cart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched, which before was drawn eaſily loaded, by four or five Horſes, but of a ſudden, became almoſt unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, in plain Ground, and half unloaded, by a much greater ſtrength: So have all things gon with us, as if they were Inchanted, for the greateſt part of this year. And ſo ſudden and great an <hi>Alteration,</hi> doth of it ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and provoke our Conſideration; but the danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſequences thereof, which have already occurred, or are within view, much more.</p>
            <p>The late wonderful <hi>Revolution</hi> which is looked upon as our Deliverance, was <hi>Compleated,</hi> if we compute from the Arrival of the Prince, to the <hi>Exit</hi> of King <hi>James,</hi> within the ſpace of forty three days; and if we extend it to the day when the Prince was Proclaimed King, it amounts but to one hundred days: But upon <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day He was Addreſſed to by the Lords, and two days after, by the Members of the former Parliaments, and the Aldermen and Common Council of the City, to take upon him the <hi>Adminiſtration of Publick Affairs,</hi> both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Military,</hi> and the Diſpoſal of the <hi>Publick Revenue,</hi> and to take into his particular care, the then preſent <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Ireland.</hi> All which, the day following, He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and undertook.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172724:5"/>
            <p>Among thoſe four things recommended in general to the Prince, and undertaken by him, were ſome things comprehended, which could not then be compleatly done by him; as the Conſtitution of Civil Officers, and of Lord Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants, and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the <hi>Militia.</hi> All that could then be done by him in theſe matters, was only to conſider, and reſolve upon fit Perſons for theſe Employments, to be Authorized as ſoon as might be. But this was a matter of ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to be ſetled as ſoon as might be, as in other reſpects, ſo more particularly, that the more Forces might have been the ſooner ſpared for <hi>Ireland.</hi> For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Diſpoſition of the People, the ordinary <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> being in good hands, would have been ſufficient for the Security of this Nation. But, whatever was the matter, neither were the Civil Magiſtrates in the ſeveral Counties, that is, the <hi>Juſtices of Peace,</hi> nor the <hi>Militia,</hi> ſetled in many Months after.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Conſequence</hi> of the ſpeedy ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or reducing of that Nation, was very great; not only for the Security, Eaſe, and Benefit of this, but moreover and eſpecially, in order to the <hi>common Deſign of the Confederates,</hi> that we might have been in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to have Attacqued the common Enemy on the one ſide, as they did on the other; which we being anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Succeſs, and our Enemies under no ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation, might have brought the common Deſign to perfection; and which is of higher Conſideration, have produced what the Providence of God had put an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity into our Hands to do, directed us to, and was ready to have conducted us to perform. And how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal may be the Conſequence of this failure, if it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from any neglect in us, as God alone compleatly knows, ſo I am unwilling to declare what I ſuſpect, nor perhaps is it fit for me to do it. But thus much of the <hi>Matter of Fact</hi> in this caſe, is certain and commonly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172724:6"/>known, that the Arms and Ammunition which were ſent, whenever that was, but to that one poor Town of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-Derry,</hi> which ſhut up their Gates the ninth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> declared for the Prince of <hi>Aurange,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and immediately ſent hither for ſpeedy Relief, Arrived not there till the twentieth of <hi>March,</hi> nor the Forees ſent with <hi>Cunningham</hi> and <hi>Richards</hi> till the fifteenth of <hi>April;</hi> and then inſtead of Relief, by deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Service, proved only a Diſcouragement to them. And though ſome others came near the ſeventh of <hi>June,</hi> yet were not thoſe poor Creatures actually relieved till the thirtieth of <hi>July;</hi> when from ſeven Thouſand five hundred brave Regimented Men, they were reduced to about four Thouſand three Hundred; though nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, why that might not have been done full as well, ſix Weeks before.</p>
            <p>Proportionable to this, for the Relief of that Town, was the Progreſs of our Affairs for the <hi>Reducing of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> That which might with eaſe have been done at firſt, grew daily more and more difficult; the Difficulties increaſing faſter than our Preparations; inſomuch, that <hi>March</hi> 8. King <hi>William</hi> ſpeaking to the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, concerning the deplorble Condition of <hi>Ireland,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That he thought it not adviſable to attempt the reducing of it with leſs than Twenty Thouſand Horſe and Foot. Difficulties ſhould, and uſually do excite ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Spirits to the more vigorous Action: And this, no doubt, was the Intention of this King in that Speech: Notwithſtanding long it was ere we could be ready to tranſport our Forces; and when all things were expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ready for that purpoſe, how they anſwered the General's expectations, muſt be left to his own Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the more particular Examination of them, who are not only concern'd, but are in Place and Authority to do it; it being commonly believed, they were not ſo well as ought to have been. And when they were at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172724:6"/>laſt Tranſported, which was not till about the middle of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> it ſeems they were not ſuch as the General thought fit to engage with the Enemy, though ſo lately baffled before <hi>London-Derry;</hi> eſpecially their Carriages not coming to him before the 24th of <hi>September;</hi> nor have they to this day, done any conſiderable Service.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is likely, the wary old General might decline any Engagement, in dayly Expectation of the <hi>Daniſh Supplies</hi> to have been with him long ſince, yet ſo unhappily hath that alſo fallen out, that the Expectation of them, hath proved only a Diſappointment to us, and perhaps a greater Diſappointment than ever their Service may repair. Beſides, the Seaſon of the year is now ſo far gon, that they are more like to prove a burden this Winter, than any advantage to us. And what may now become not only of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but of the Forces we have already ſent thither, is very doubtful; ſo that we have in a manner, already loſt all the Expence of this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and are in danger to loſe a great part of our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alſo.</p>
            <p>And now, if from Land we deſcend to take a Proſpect of the Progreſs of <hi>our Affairs at Sea,</hi> we ſhall ſtill find all alike: The two famous Nations for Action at Sea, not only baffled by the ſole Power of <hi>France,</hi> but our loſſes in Men by <hi>Sickneſs</hi> and <hi>Mortalities</hi> greater than by <hi>Fight,</hi> and in our Merchandiſe and Trade, not leſs than our Expences: And, as if the Power of our Enemies were not enough to annoy us, after all, (if the Complaints of our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and their Mariners be true) our Ships have been made a Prey by thoſe who ſhould have been their Guard and Convoy, and were imployed for that Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And if we return again to Land, and conſider the <hi>State of the Countrie,</hi> we ſhall there find all our Country Commodities at ſo low a Rate, as will hardly pay Wages and other neceſſary charges, beſides reaſonable Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Families: And this Condition made harder by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172724:7"/>Taxes already granted and Levyed, and thoſe unſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpent, and more expected. And ſuch a Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the great Expectation, which was general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceived of a happy change of Affairs, muſt needs produce an unhappy change in Mens minds.</p>
            <p>And if we apply our ſelves to conſider the Proceedings of <hi>our Councils,</hi> the great Council of the Nation, and the King's Privy Council, we may there more eaſily find the Original Root, Occaſions and Authors of all theſe Miſchiefs, than any ſuch ſound Reſolutions or Counſels, as ever were, or are likely either to have prevented, or now to redreſs the ſame. A bold Speech, this I confeſs it is; but being ſaid, not maliciouſly out of any evil Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or Deſign, but out of Zeal for the common Safety, and other good Ends, nor of particular Perſons, I doubt not but the Evidence of Truth, and the Conſciences of moſt, will excuſe and acquit me. And yet I muſt be bold to ſay, there are ſome things paſſed, of which none of them all who were preſent, or concern'd, can acquit or excuſe themſelves.</p>
            <p>Such was one of the firſt Acts of the Convention, the Form of their <hi>Order for the Thankſgiving.</hi> And if any one dare preſume to excuſe that as a ſmall matter, I dare be bold to ſay, he hath but little ſenſe of the Majeſty of God concerned in it, of his extraordinary Mercy and Goodneſs in the Deliverance, of the dangerous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of ſuch a fault in the beginning of their Conſul-rations, or what an Indication it was of an unhappy Temper and Diſpoſition prevalent in that Aſſembly. But had the Form been altogether faultleſs, to order a ſolemn Thankſgiving to God, and never after do any real Act of Gratitude for his Honour and Service, when pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Swearing, and other Impieties and Wickedneſs were grown to that height of Impudence and Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is ſuch a thing, as would be reſented with Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by a mortal Man, and was more likely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172724:7"/>a ſuſpenſion at leaſt of the Favours of Providence we enjoyed, than a continuance thereof. But of that more elſewhere.</p>
            <p>One of the next things they did, was the ordering of a Committee for the buſineſs of <hi>Ireland:</hi> But, what have they done ever ſince in that buſineſs? Either nothing at all, or nothing to the purpoſe, as the Event, and what I have before taken notice of, doth plainly ſhew and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate. And yet it is plain, there wanted not mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enough proper for their conſideration. There were <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants enough in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to have defended themſelves, and ſecured that Kingdom, had they not been diſarmed, and their Arms contrary to Law, put into the hands of <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and notwithſtanding that, had they but had Arms ſent them in time; And had they needed ſome ſmall Body of men at firſt, to whom they might have repaired, we had more in Arms and Pay here than we needed, and therefore, not only refuſed many who offered their Service, but Disbanded many of thoſe we had. We had Ships alſo at the ſame charge, whether employed upon that Service or any other. Why then were not Men and Arms too, ſent them in time, while our Men were Animated with Succeſs, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> under a Conſternation? Why not we as forward as the <hi>French?</hi> And why, inſtead of ſending to them, were ſo many of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> who had been in Arms here, ſuffered to return, and not rather employed in ſome Service of the Confederates, at leaſt of the Emperour againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> if they might not have been truſted againſt the <hi>French?</hi> And when by our neglect at firſt, there was need of a greater Force, if we had then Men enough in Arms, why were not more raiſed at home, of thoſe who before had offered themſelves, of thoſe who were Disbanded, and of thoſe who were forced from their Eſtates in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and wanted Maintenance here? But we muſt ſend for Forreigners without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172724:8"/>of Parliament, and ſo inour the blame we caſt upon others; and ſend for ſuch, which muſt protract the time, when we might as well have been certainly provided at home much ſooner? And whereas all this may ſeem to have been managed either for the real Service of King <hi>James,</hi> or for a colour, to bring in a Foreign Force for the Security of ſuch as having been true, neither to Him, nor to their Country, durſt now truſt neither, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to impoſe upon the preſent King, and under the old pretence of his Service, get into their own hands a power to enſlave their Country; it had been worth the Enquiry, how it was ſerviceable to the preſent Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? and who were the Adviſers and principal Agents in it? And certainly ſuch matters as this had been no improper nor unuſual Buſineſs, for the Conſideration of a Parliament.</p>
            <p>The next and greateſt matter of all, of civil Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, was <hi>the long Debate about the Abdication.</hi> This took them up little leſs than three Weeks time. And though there was reaſon enough to declare the Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of King <hi>James</hi> under his Circumſtances, an Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Government, he having before notoriouſly endeavoured the Subverſion of the Conſtitution, actually, in divers great Inſtances, Violated the Fundamental Laws, given juſt cauſe of War to the Prince, and of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Vindication of their Rights, to the People; and after all, by recalling the Writs for a Parliament, refuſed a legal Determination of the matters in Queſtion, all which make it plainly, rather the flight of a Criminal from Juſtice, than of an innocent Man <hi>Metus cauſa &amp; cum Animo revertendi;</hi> and a Ceſſion or Dereliction of the Government in Fact, which his deliberate Violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons declare he had before Deſerted in Affection; yet as if they indeed layed the whole ſtreſs upon the Departure; and the other matters charged againſt <hi>King James</hi> were not criminal or puniſhable, ſo much as in <hi>his Miniſters,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172724:8"/>Counſellors, and Accomplices,</hi> or at leaſt doubted their own Authority as a Parliament, <hi>not one</hi> of thoſe, who by their wicked Counſels and Compliances, betrayed not only their Country, but their King himſelf, whom they pretended to ſerve, into ſuch miſchiefs as were like to have been fatal to both, (whatever yet may come of it) hath yet been <hi>brought to condign Puniſhment, or ſo much as called in Queſtion</hi> upon a fair Tryal; quite contrary to all the Practice of our Anceſtors; who always puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Counſellors, Miniſters and Agents in ſuch Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, but rarely the Prince himſelf, unleſs in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary caſes directly tending to the Deſtruction or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Government, as this did.</p>
            <p>And whereas upon ſuch a Revolution, one of the moſt neceſſary things to be done, eſpecially when meeting with ſuch Oppoſition as this hath, and is yet like to do, is <hi>to Remove</hi> as much as may be all <hi>Occaſions of Difference, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite all</hi> Parties in a firm Agreement, <hi>for a Mutual Aſſiſtance</hi> in civil Matters, ſuch hath been the Jealouſies, Animoſities, and prepoſterous Zeal of many, that a great part of the moſt ſober and ſerious People of this Nation, are to this day, kept out of the Service of their Country, and the moſt debauched and profligate freely let in; and let in with the groſſeſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of Sacred things, that hath, I think, been known in any Chriſtian Nation; and no expedient can yet be agreed on, though in a matter of ſo great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance.</p>
            <p>And to ſum up all that belongs to this Conſideration of the Parliament, in one Word, they have been all along infeſted with a Spirit of Diviſion, ſo prevalent upon them, that they have ſcarce done one brave and clever Action, nor ſo much as enquired to any purpoſe, into the Cauſes, and principal Authors of the evil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of our Affairs, ever ſince they met.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:172724:9"/>
            <p>Should we come nearer to the King himſelf, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the more ſecret Proceedings of his <hi>Privy Council,</hi> and great Miniſters of State, 'tis poſſible we ſhould come ſo much the nearer yet, to the Fountain head of much of this Unhappineſs: For it muſt all have been either the Effect or Diſappointment of their Counſels. But ſuch an Enquiry is a buſineſs ſo proper for the grand Inqueſt of the Nation, that it is fit to be left to them to do it effectually.</p>
            <p>But as for <hi>the King</hi> himſelf, this is apparent to the World, that the embroil'd, if not loſt condition of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the loſs of this Summers Aſſiſtance to His Confederates, is a great Eclipſe and Diminution of that Honour, which the ſucceſs of his former Proceedings had acquired; and was of ſo great Importance to him for the farther Progreſs of His Affairs.</p>
            <p>But I need not proceed farther on ſo ungrateful a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; the Inſtances I have already produced, are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſhew a <hi>great and unhappy Change</hi> in the Courſe and Progreſs of our Affairs, from ſo ſmooth and proſperous, that formidable Armies could give no check or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, but vaniſhed like Smoke before the Wind, to ſo rough and diſturbed, and that ſo univerſal in all, that neither Abroad nor at Home, at Sea or at Land, in Country or in Council, do we find any chearful face of Affairs, but every where Rubs, Impediments, Failures and Diſappointments, and our way fenced up that we cannot paſs.</p>
            <p>So great a change as this, is enough to move the curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of an unconcerned Spectator to enquire into the <hi>true Cauſes</hi> of it, much more ought our own concern to move us to do it, with no leſs care and diligence, than a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and faithful Chyrurgeon would uſe, in the ſearch of ſome dangerous Wound or Sore. Nor would it be hard to diſcover the particular, immediate Cauſes of many of theſe things; but to reſt in them, would prove but a ſhallow
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172724:9"/>and ſuperficial Speculation; and the Application of means for the redreſs of them alone, could not be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have better effect than the application of a Plaiſter to a deep and ulcerous Wound. Here is ſo great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of ſo many and various evil Symptoms, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular immediate Cauſes conſpiring to croſs and diſappoint us, as is a plain Indication of ſome more ſecret and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful common cauſe influencing all. They are men of no very clear, (but clouded) Minds, or of no very ſtrict Obſervation, who having any conſiderable time been converſant with Men and Buſineſs in the World, do not feel in themſelves, and perceive in others, that the moſt minute concerns of men, are under the Conduct and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen of certain inviſible Powers. Though Providence and Induſtry often ſucceed, yet we ſee them often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated; and lucky and unlucky Hits, as we call them, and thoſe many times unaccountable, prevail above and againſt both; and that not once or twice, but in a long courſe together. And had we but the underſtanding of <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Aſs, we might diſcern, that an Angel of the Lord is ſtanding in our way to ſtop our Progreſs; and that this great change, is indeed <hi>Mutatio dextrae Altiſſimi. Iſrael</hi> hath ſinned and tranſgreſſed, and therefore cannot proſper: Our ſtrength is departed from us, and we are become like other men: Neither will it return, unleſs the curſed thing be found out and removed. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is our buſineſs, which this change of ſucceſs loudly calls us to, to find out the Sin that keeps good things from us, and to diſſipate the Cloud that intercepts the benign Influences of Heaven. And to that end, it will be fit to return to that Period of the Revolutien, the Exit of King <hi>James,</hi> and the Arrival of the Prince at the Roval Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and the confines of the Metropolis of the Nation, and conſider what Indications have ſince occurred.</p>
            <p>Here he was met and attended by moſt of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and a numerous concourſe of the Gentry and People
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172724:10"/>of all Ranks and Qualities, from all parts of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the very next Lord's Day, were the following ADMONITIONS very ſealonably given to him, and to all then preſent, from the Pulpit; and ſoon after by his Highneſ's ſpecial Command, to all others from the Preſs, by a Perſon of great Name, who having ſhewed from the amazing Concurrence of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the late Revolution, that it was the LORD's DOING, he makes ſome <hi>Reflections</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p>One whereof he thus Expreſſeth:</p>
            <p>P. 22. <hi>If we will carry on, and perfect this Marvellous</hi> WORK OF GOD, <hi>we muſt ſtudy to be ſuch, that God may not repent him of the good which he ſeems to have prepared for us. While we are under ſuch a happy Influence of Heaven, we muſt not</hi> RAISE UP SUCH AN INTERPOSITION <hi>between it and us, as may not only make us loſe this happy Opportunity, but turn it to a Curſe by the ill uſe we may make of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another he Expreſſeth in theſe Words:</p>
            <p>P. 20. <hi>If this</hi> WORK OF GOD <hi>poſſeſs us with the Veneration which is due to it, We ought</hi> NOT TO STOP THE COURSE OF IT, <hi>till it has had its full Effect; nor to</hi> DAUB <hi>matters by ſlight and palliating Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. We ſee now before us the moſt</hi> GLORIOUS BEGINNING <hi>of a noble Change of the whole face of Affairs, both with relation to Religion, and the Peace of</hi> Europe, <hi>that we could have wiſh'd for. It is ſo far beyond our Hopes, that we durſt ſcarce let our Wiſhes go ſo far: We may, if we are not wanting to our ſelves, and to the Conjunctures before us, hope to ſee that which may be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Prophetick Stile, termed a New Heaven, and a New Earth. But if a Spirit of Jealouſie and Murmuring, of Impatience and Faction, and of returning back to that out of which God has ſo ſignally extricated us, grows up; ſo that inſtead of reaping the Fruits that we have now in Proſpect,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172724:10"/>we have not Souls big enough, nor Hearts good enough to carry this on to Perfection, then we may juſtly fear our being</hi> DEIVERED UP <hi>to all thoſe Evils from which we will not be healed,</hi> &amp;c. And a little after, <hi>There is ſcarce any</hi> INDICATION <hi>more certain of the Sins of a Nation being grown up to that height, that it muſt be deſtroyed, than the</hi> MISCARRIAGE <hi>of ſo great a Deliverance as God has wrought for us, which will be an Eternal Blot on the Wiſdom of the Nation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again: P. 24. <hi>In order to the preventing the return of the like Evils, We muſt avoid the</hi> RELAPSING <hi>into the like Sins. It is neither the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion nor Wiſdom of Councils, nor the Strength of Fleets or Armies, that will ſecure us from the Judgments of God, which we may expect will fall upon us with an extraordinary redoubling, of ſeven times heavier than any thing that we have yet ſeen or known, if thoſe that are filthy, will be filthy ſtill.—If Men think that their Fears are over, and that therefore they may give themſelves up to work Wickedneſs without Reſtraint; then we may juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a return of the like, if not of greater Miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And toward the Concluſion: P. 31. <hi>If in all that we do, we take not</hi> Care to have God ever on our Sides, <hi>it will be eaſie for him to blaſt all Councils, and to defeat even the greateſt and beſt laid Deſigns. We have now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Eyes one of the ſignalleſt Inſtances that is in any Hiſtory, of the Inſtability of all humane things,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, ſome may imagine that we are ſafe, becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be</hi> daſhed on the ſame Rock, <hi>about which we ſee ſo great a Shipwreck: But alas! If we provoke God to hide his Face, and to withdraw his Protection from us, his Ways are paſt finding out: He can bring Ruine and Deſtruction on us from that Hand, from which perhaps we apprehend the leaſt. If Proſperity and Succeſs blow any up, and make them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God, and all the Vows that they made to him, he will never want Means and Methods to make them return to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to remember him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:172724:11"/>
            <p>To theſe I will ſubjoyn one more delivered by the ſame Perſon upon the ſolemn Occaſion of the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in theſe Words:</p>
            <p>Page 3. <hi>Thoſe who are raiſed up to a high Eminence of Dignity, are ſo much the more accountable both to God and Man, not only for all the Ill, which either they themſelves, or others acting in their Name, or by their Example may have done; but likewiſe for all the Good which they might have done, but did not. And as they have much to anſwer for to God, ſo likewiſe men expect much from them.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all truths, and ſo plain truths, that there need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no extraordinary Spirit of Propheſie to reveal them: and yet I doubt not but we may ſay truly, <hi>This ſpake he not of himſelf, but</hi> being ordered to preach on ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>he propheſied.</hi> If we believe that this great work was <hi>the work of God,</hi> in whoſe hand are the hearts of all men, why ſhould we queſtion but he who directed the Wind at Sea, directed alſo now at their arrival here, the motions of this mans heart to ſo ſeaſonable and neceſſary Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the farther promotion of that work, which he had ſo eminently favoured hitherto? And the great change in the progreſs of affairs, which we have ſince ſeen, confirms the ſame, inaſmuch as it ſhews the Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions to have been not a little neceſſary. And if that be ſo, it is the more likely that <hi>ſome Miſcarriage</hi> there hath been, contrary not only to certain Duties, but to ſome ſuch particular expreſs Admonition; which is a great aggravation of that fault, which hath had the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy effect to raiſe up ſuch an <hi>Interpoſition</hi> between the happy Influence of Heaven and us.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:172724:11"/>
            <p>The next thing then to be enquired is whoſe, and what this Miſcarriage may be? The perſons concerned in the Succeſs and Management both were the Prince himſelf, his Counſellors, Miniſters, and thoſe about him, and among them he eſpecially who gave thoſe Admonitions, the Convention, the Army and the Navy; in the Succeſs alone the people of theſe Nations, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Confederates beyond Sea, whoſe Deſign is as much affected with it as the concern of any other. But whoever elſe might be concerned in the Fault, becauſe the Prince was not only principally concerned in the Succeſs and Management both, but had before been made ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious an Inſtrument that nothing could ſtop his Advance, it is not reaſonable to believe that he ſhould have been at all deſerted by the propitious Powers of Heaven, without ſome Offence given by himſelf, either by his own Act or Neglect, or by Participation with ſome other. And to diſcover that, what it might be, is a matter of great importance, and requires no leſs Fidelity in any man to endeavour it, than Skill to do it effectually; Fidelity to God, to himſelf now King, to his Country, and Good Will to a moſt juſt and honourable Cauſe, and to all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it. And all this I hope is ground enough for plain dealing,</p>
            <p>I cannot think of this King without thinking alſo of his Predeceſſors in the Throne of theſe Kingdoms, from whom he is perſonally deſcended, and now ſucceeds in their Eſtate: Had he been only perſonally deſcended from them, he had not been ſo far concerned in the Fate of their Family; but having now accepted their Seat and Right, he thereby ſucceeds in their Obligations, and muſt either diſcharge their Debt by Reformation of what they have in that Capacity done amiſs, or bear their Iniquity, and ſucceed alſo in their Puniſhment. They had all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Providence in their acceſs to the Throne, and ſome of them in a ſpecial manner, even beyond their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172724:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>or Hope; but none more than this. But they all deſerted imprudently the Conduct, and ungratefully the Service of that benign Providence, and following their own ways, were thereupon deſerted by it, and <hi>Rehoboam</hi>-like left to the unſound and pernicious Counſels of Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, and unfaithful ſelf-ſeeking Favourites, who for their own ſiniſter ends divided the Common Cauſe, and ſet up a Separate Intereſt of Prerogative againſt Law, and King againſt the People, and turned the Court and Church into a <hi>Combined Faction.</hi> This hath been the Stumbling Stone and <hi>Rock of Offence</hi> to all the former; and I know not any thing that can be more dangerous to this, and if he be not well aware of it, to the remainder of that Royal Family, if not to Monarchy it ſelf in this Nation.</p>
            <p>This is a matter of ſo great conſequence for the Peace and Proſperity both of King and People to be well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that it deſerves a more particular conſideration. And theſe <hi>two Obſervations</hi> will make it very plain and apparent. 1. It is certain that by the Conſtitution of our Government the King can legally do very little, but by the Advice of ſome legal Council. The <hi>Councils,</hi> by whoſe Advice he is to proceed, are 1. The Great Council of the Kingdom, the <hi>Parliament.</hi> 2. The Lords, who are <hi>Conciliarii Nati.</hi> 3. The <hi>Kings Council for matters of Law,</hi> anciently conſiſting of other and more perſons, beſides the Judges and Sergeants, than now are conſulted with: And 4. The <hi>Privy Council.</hi> But <hi>Secret Cabals</hi> and <hi>Cabinet Councils</hi> of Favourites are neither agreeable to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſtitution, nor have been ever ſucceſsful, but always pernicious and deſtructive, to ſuch Kings as have moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed on them. In what is done by advice of Legal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, the King is always, and ought to be, excuſed, and the adviſers anſwerable for it: But what is done by illegal Councils, is imputed to the King himſelf, and uſually produceth Diſcontents in the people. And of this was K. <hi>Ch.</hi> II. very ſenſible, when in his Declaration <hi>Apr.</hi> 20
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172724:12"/>1679. he tells the Privy Council, <hi>He is ſorry for the ill ſucceſs he hath found in this courſe, and ſenſible of the ill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of affairs, from that, and ſome unhappy Accidents, which have raiſed great Jealouſies and Diſſatisfaction among his good Subjects, and thereby left the Crown and Government in a condition too weak for thoſe dangers we have reaſon to fear both at home and abroad.</hi> And then declaring his Hopes <hi>that thoſe</hi> evils <hi>may be prevented by a courſe of wiſe and ſteady Councels for the future, and theſe Kingdoms grow again to make ſuch a figure as they have formerly done in the World, and as they may always do, if our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NION and CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CT were equal to our Force;</hi> and his Reſolution <hi>to that end to lay aſide the uſe</hi> he had made <hi>of any ſingle Miniſtry or private Adviſers, and to conſtitute ſuch a Privy Council,</hi> as for number and choice may be fit, and to govern <hi>by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Advice of ſuch a Council together with the frequent uſe of his great Council of Parliament;</hi> he adds, <hi>which he takes to be <hi>the true Ancient Conſtitution of this State and Government.</hi>
               </hi> The mode was before, and ſoon taken up again, to draw the Orders, matters of greateſt moment being firſt reſolved in a private Cabal, as made by the King <hi>in Council,</hi> inſtead of <hi>by advice of the Council;</hi> and to prefix the Names of all preſent, inſtead of each, who conſented to them, ſubſcribing his own; ſo that none could be charged with what was done but the King himſelf; which was no leſs prejudicial to the King and Kingdom, than contrary to ancient cuſtome and the good Polity of our Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>The <hi>other obſervation</hi> is this: What at firſt, and for ſome time, was ordered by the Aſſemblies of Chriſtians, the <hi>Clergy</hi> in proceſs of time aſſumed to themſelves to order alone: and what was then done by the Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the Clergy, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> afterward aſſumed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves alone with their Chancellors. And in ſome ages after <hi>the Biſhops of Rome</hi> made the like Encroachments upon the Right of all, eſpecially in matters of moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172724:13"/>as the diſpoſing of Biſhopricks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At laſt <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. with us perceiving the injuſtice of the Papal uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, inſtead of reſtoring things to the right and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Inſtitution, ſo far prevailed with his Parliament, as to get all annexed to the Crown. And no doubt this was thought a ſpecial acqueſt, and much for the advantage of the King and his Succeſſors: but it proved like ill got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten goods, a pernicious morſel. For it ſoon excited the moſt aſpiring of the Clergy to ſeek by Flatteries to obtain their Favour, who had the diſpoſal of the great Preferments of the Church. This ſoon produced falſe Notions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Royal Power; and the intereſt of thoſe who deſigned that Profeſſion made thoſe Notions eaſily ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed without much examination; till at laſt the very youth in the Univerſities were levened with them: and being ſo early ſeaſoned therewith, they could not but take deep root in many honeſt and well-meaning perſons. Again, this muſt needs have the like influence upon Kings, who are of themſelves as apt to aſſume, as Flatterers are to attribute, whatever tends to the enlargement of their Power. On the other ſide, the greateſt part of the Nation, that is all, who have no temptation to Flattery, well knowing their own Rights, could not be wheadled out of them with miſtaken Names and groundleſs Notions. And from theſe two Roots have ſprung that <hi>combined Faction,</hi> which hath ſo long and often occaſioned the ſhaking this Throne with ſuch violent concuſſions, and will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly overturn it, if things be not reſtored in time to their right order.</p>
            <p>And to prevent ſo great a miſchief, it may be farther ſerviceable to obſerve the Difference between this Faction, or the <hi>Factious Church of England,</hi> and the <hi>true Church of England.</hi> For as the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> arrogates to it ſelf the Name and Title of Catholick, and excludes all others who are not of that Communion, from any right to it, and yet is it ſelf at beſt, but a part of that which is indeed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172724:13"/>the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> ſo the great Zealots for this Faction, under the Name of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> will hardly deign the Name of Church of <hi>England men,</hi> to any who run not to the ſame exceſs with themſelves; though if the matter be rightly computed, they will not be found ſo great a part of thoſe who do juſtly come under that deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, much leſs of the People and Strength of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as they may ſeem to ſome, and would be thought to be. For of thoſe, who are not inferiour to any either in Conformity to the Church, both in Doctrine and Worſhip, and that not out of any ſneaking or crafty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, but judgment and choice; or in true Loyalty and Fidelity to the King in his Juſt and Legal Rights; they are as little inferiour in Number or Intereſt, who notwithſtanding, preferring Chriſtianity it ſelf before any particular Church, and a compleat genuine Loyalty to the intire State and Conſtitution, before a partial pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Loyalty to any party in it, do not think themſelves obliged, either by any Duty to the preſent Church, to neglect the great Duties of Chriſtianity, Charity, and reaſonable condeſcention in things indifferent; or by my Reverence to Anceſtors, to neglect what is neceſſary at this time, as well for Peace and Unity, as for ſupply and improvement of what they themſelves had begun, and declare was not then compleat and perfect: Or laſtly, by any partial Loyalty, or even Oath of Fidelity to the King (which extends but to his juſt Rights, and thoſe too for the benefit of the whole, ſo that he cannot alienate or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them at his own pleaſure) to deſert the Rights of their Country, and the confeſſed true ancient Conſtitution of the State and Government. And theſe ſolid Principles being grounded upon Truth and Juſtice, wherein another great part of the Nation is equally concerned, muſt needs prevail at laſt againſt the falſe pretences of a violent Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which hath no other ſupport but Ambition, Avarice and Animoſity, animated by the Favour or Compliance
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172724:14"/>of flattered, eaſie, and deceived Prince, though they create no little diſturbance for ſome time, for the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their great beloved <hi>Diana.</hi> Beſides, if we conſider the tendency of the Motions of the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence at this time, it is not likely that our Lord will much longer ſuffer ſuch unprofitable Servants in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, but ſpue out the <hi>Laodicean</hi> Faction out of his mouth, unleſs they ſpeedily mend their manners. But to return</p>
            <p>The Arm of God, that is his Divine Providence, was not leſs apparent in that Revolution, which reſtored <hi>King Charles</hi> II. than in this, which hath brought this King to the Throne; nor leſs obliging. Nor were the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities then leſs than now, which were put into his hands to have made himſelf and theſe Kingdoms happy; but he inſenſible of that Illuſtrious Providence, and regardleſs of his Word, gave up himſelf to Senſuality, aery phanſies, and crafty Policies, and moſt ungratefully by an evil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, transfuſed a torrent of all kind of Vice, Fraud, Injuſtice, Profaneneſs, Contempt of Religion, and all manner of impudent Wickedneſs, all over the Nation. And all this deſcended as a charge upon <hi>his Succeſſor,</hi> either to be expunged and diſcharged by ſolemn Humiliation and effectual Reformation, or to be anſwered and born by himſelf in the Meaſure of Puniſhment and Affliction to be laid upon him. But this was a matter which had too much of the Influences and Approbation of his own party, to be checked or reſtrained by him. On the contrary, it was by him aggravated with additions of ſuch violences and bare-fac'd bold illegal attempts, and thoſe for ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful an end, the reſtitution of the Romiſh Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as his Brother had either more conſideration, or leſs courage, than ever to venture upon, till the Land caſt him out; thoſe very Perſons, who had baſely betrayed him into thoſe miſchiefs, by pretences of Loyalty, and magnifying Prerogative above the Law and the Truth, and by flatterring Addreſſes, being many as forward as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172724:14"/>any to conſpire againſt him, when their own Intereſt was touched, and others to come into the prevailing Party; and will likewiſe betray, whoever they are, who ſhall truſt or rely upon them.</p>
            <p>This was <hi>the State, in which the Prince at his Arrival found this Kingdom:</hi> And if this was <hi>the Marvellous work of God</hi> to bring him hither, we may eaſily perceive from hence what was <hi>the Princes Work</hi> for which he was brought. Shall we think it was to drive out Popery and Arbitrarineſs, that we might injoy our Rights, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the greater Liberty to profane a purer Religion, and by impudent violation of it, bring all Religion into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt? No, no, theſe were but ſuch acceſſions of the Principal Evil, as made way for the ejection of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy deluded Prince, as well for neglect of his Duty, in not reſtraining the over-ſpreading Impiety and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the Nation, as for his own additional tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. And if after all it be not now reformed, it will certainly prove ſuch a Canker and Root of bitterneſs, as will ſoon grow up to produce the like evil fruit again of it ſelf, without any ſuch additionals. For can any one imagine that the Abominations of Debauchery and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety can be leſs offenſive to the moſt Holy God, than the Abominations of Popery? Or that the Popiſh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, Errours, and Impoſtures, can be more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to him than impudent and preſumptious violation, and notorious profanation of a purer Religion, and open contempt of all? If not, then the Reformation of thoſe Impieties and Wickedneſs, which have over-ſpread the Nation, but eſpecially the Nobility and Gentry, and moſt of all the Army, which ſoon ſubmitted to him, was a ſpecial and principal part of his Work, which he was conducted, and as it were, led by the hand to do. And therefore plainly without more ſaying, by neglect of this was <hi>the Fault</hi> committed: In this was the <hi>ſtop put</hi> to the courſe of this Work of God: This was <hi>the Good,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172724:15"/>which might have been done</hi> but was not, and is therefore to be accounted for both to God and Man: This neglect it being one of the great ſins of the former Kings, was therefore now a <hi>Relapſe</hi> into the ſame: This was a neglect, of <hi>Care to have God ever on our ſide:</hi> And by this was <hi>the Interpoſition raiſed</hi> between the happy influence of Heaven and us: A fault committed againſt a great Duty, after ſo admirable a Divine Conduct to it, and ſo many expreſs and weighty Cautions and Admonitions.</p>
            <p>And yet this is not all, for the ſame Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which ſo ſeaſonably gave him theſe Adminitions by one, as ſeaſonably ſent him <hi>a Specimen of a Delaration againſt Debauchery</hi> by another, with no mean Motives cloſely couched in a ſhort Letter. It was Compoſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Princes Authority, and the State of Affairs as it then was, the expreſſions of command directed only to the Armies and Souldiery, who were properly ſubject to his Command, what had reſpect to the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or future Parliament, in expreſſions only of hope and expectation. And as much as this might have been done by any General of an Army; but God with the ſucceſs, he had given to him, had given him alſo that Authority and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in the minds of all men, which would have extended the Effect of ſuch a Declaration to thoſe to whom it was not directed; and he would alſo undoubtedly, had the Prince but firſt declar'd, and then ſhewed his Reſolution by deſtributing his Favours according to mens Conformity thereunto, have made all as quietly comply therewith, as he made the Army ſubmit to his Power, and have made this ſecond atchievement no leſs Glorious to him than the former, not only for confirmation, but augmentation alſo of his Honour and Authority. His very Preſence ſhould have diſperſed the Wickedneſs of this Nation; and the Divine Preſence ſhould have continued with him, and have given him Reſt and Happineſs. But here was the Fault, an unhappy, though I hope not yet fatal, fault committed.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:172724:15"/>
            <p>The Wiſe Governour of the World, whom he calls out to any ſpecial Service, them he uſually, if not always, leads to ſome ſpecial <hi>Tryal of</hi> their <hi>Fidelity;</hi> wherein, if they acquit themſelves well, he makes them afterward very happy and proſperous, but if ill, either wholly lays them aſide, or leaves them to great difficulties, till they recover themſelves by Repentance, and ſome very gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Act of Fidelity. This Declaration was preſented to him the ſame day in the morning, on which the Lords in the afternoon preſented him with an Addreſs to accept of the Adminiſtration till a free Parliament could be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled. That both theſe propoſals were preſented to him on the ſame day, was not without the Diſpoſal of the Divine Providence. The one was for the Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, the other in appearance for his own Honour; and both made up a plain compleat <hi>Trial.</hi> And the latter he accepted; but the former hath been neglected to this day. The <hi>cauſe</hi> of ſuch neglect is principally either the Faſcination of <hi>Proſperity,</hi> which diſpoſeth men to forget God, or the Deceitfulneſs of <hi>Worldly Wiſdom,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays them to forſake him, and apply themſelves to ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſenſible means to ſecure what they do in fact prefer before him. When theſe two meet they make a ſtrong <hi>Temptation;</hi> but againſt both he had the freſh Experience of the Favour of God, and of the irreſiſtable Power of the Divine Providence over him, and making all things eaſy and plain before him; and this made the fault the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more inexcuſable.</p>
            <p>Nor is this ſo ſmall and inconſiderable a matter as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual men may be apt to think it, which poſſibly may be the better perceived if we take notice more diſtinctly of the ſeveral <hi>particular Ingredients</hi> comprehended in it, and how aptly certain <hi>like particulars,</hi> of which the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Change is compoſed, do correſpond to them. And <hi>firſt,</hi> if we conſider it only as a <hi>Neglect</hi> of Duty <hi>and Deſertion</hi> for the preſent of a principal part of the Work, to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172724:16"/>which he was led in ſo extraordinary a manner by the propitious Providence of God, is it not as plain that that propitious Providence, which before made his Progreſs ſo exceeding ſmooth, eaſie, and ſucceſsful, hath in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſince either deſerted, or ſo neglected his affairs, that all have either gone back, ſtood ſtill, or proceeded very ſlowly. <hi>Secondly,</hi> as this Neglect was alſo a matter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs</hi> in his Lords Service, in which he was as a ſpecial Inſtrument, employed and intruſted; ſo never was Unfaithfulneſs more notorious, than in the occurrences of this laſt year, in ſuch as were employed and intruſted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, as is commonly believed, and ſhall be diſcovered in its cauſes hereafter. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it was a Neglect of his <hi>Honour,</hi> who had conferred by ſo extraordinary ſucceſs, ſo much Honour and Reputation upon him; and ſuch change of ſucceſs is uſually attended with proportionable diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Honour and Reputation. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> here was (the Root of all) a <hi>Deſertion of Dependance and Truſt</hi> in that potent Providence, which had favoured him hitherto in ſo extraordinary a manner, and recourſe to deceitful <hi>Worldly Wiſdom.</hi> It was the Unhappineſs of King <hi>James</hi> I. that after an admirable Deliverance from an horrid Popiſh Conſpiracy ready for execution, he applied himſelf firſt to connivance, and at laſt to aſſociation with Papiſts for his ſecurity; which contrary to his expectation proved the Original of all the miſchiefs, which have ſince befallen his Family: So likewiſe this Prince, after as great an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the Divine Providence over him, leſt the Kingdom ſhould return to King <hi>James,</hi> thought to deal wiſely with them, and (after <hi>Huſhai</hi>'s advice) defer this great Work, firſt till the Kingdom ſhould be ſettled, and then when he was Proclaimed King, till <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be reduced, and he ſhould have ſufficient Power (an Arm of Fleſh) to do it effectually, and in the mean time try what effect a good example and kindneſs, intruſting them with Offices and Employments in State, Army and Navy,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172724:16"/>would have upon ſuch vitious people in the end, which in like manner, contrary to his expectation, hath proved the Original of all the Impediments and Diſappointments in his affairs. <hi>O that my people had hearkened unto me, and Iſrael had walked in my ways! I ſhould ſoon have ſubdued their Enemies, and turned my hand againſt their Adverſaries. The Haters of the Lord</hi> (the Profane and Debauched) <hi>ſhould have ſubmitted themſelves unto him: but their time ſhould have endured for ever.</hi> Pſal. 81.13. <hi>Now would the Lord have eſtabliſhed thy Kingdom upon Iſrael for ever.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.13.</p>
            <p>This was <hi>the Root of the Miſcarriage: Haſt thou not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured this unto thy ſelf, in that thou haſt forſaken the Lord thy God, when he led thee by the way?</hi> Jer. 2.17. From hence hath plainly proceeded this great change of the former proſperous courſe of Affairs into ſo diſturbed, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedited and unſucceſsful, even by a natural Chain of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes after the firſt breach, but thoſe moved and promoted (by the Divine Permiſſion) by other inviſible Powers than thoſe which gave that great ſucceſs before. The preſence of ſo favourable a Providence, ought to have been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with a proportionable Magnanimity, Reſolution and Conſtancy, in dependance upon that Divine Power; but in ſuch a caſe, to ſtoop to compliance to thoſe, who ought to have been awed and ſubdued, is diſhonourable, and a great offence to thoſe Divine Powers: And if thoſe be once provok'd to withdraw, a man ſinks preſently under the Power of them, who otherwiſe ſhould have been ſubject to him. And by this Fault without doubt, and his acceptance of their State, did this Prince <hi>enter into the Fate of his Anceſtors</hi> of this Nation, and will be daily more and more involved therein, until it either prove fatal to him, or he by Repentance and ſome Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous and reſolute change of his courſe and methods, extricate himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:172724:17"/>
            <p>And it is very obſervable that he not only fell by <hi>the ſame Sin,</hi> but fell into <hi>the very ſame Faction,</hi> which for the four laſt Reigns ſucceſſively, have by their Flatteries of Princes for their private advantage, and provocations of the people by Tricks, illegal Projects and Practices, brought all thoſe miſchiefs which we have ſeen and felt, upon both: Whereas both civil Prudence, and Duty to God, <hi>i. e.</hi> Fidelity to the Conduct of his Providence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that he ſhould have maintained the Reputation and Authority he was raiſed to, made himſelf Umpire of all Parties, reſtrained the Exceſſes, and diſcouraged the Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of each, and with a mixture of Authority and equal Kindneſs to all, reduced them as near as might be to a Union, at leaſt to a mutual agreement in matters of common concern. But by the courſe of Affairs, he ſeems to have been rather paſſive than active in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof; and what Counſels prevailed therein may by the ſame alſo be perceived.</p>
            <p>Nor was it only into the ſame Faction that he fell, but into the hands <hi>of thoſe very Perſons,</hi> who in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second (for under King <hi>James</hi> they were overtopp'd by others) were the principal Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and Managers in thoſe illegal Projects, and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſcious of their own Guilt and Deſert, have by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their tools, not only hitherto obſtructed Juſtice, upon the betrayers of their King and Country, to the great diſparagement of the preſent Settlement, but ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated ſuch a mungrel party, and therewith filled many Offices of the Revenue, Army and Navy, as are real and hearty neither to this nor the former King, but intending only their own ſafety or advantage, are diſpoſed to act, as in a doubtful caſe, ſo as may beſt ſerve their turn, which ever prevail. And from this ſort of people have proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt of the Rubs and Difficulties in our Proceedings; and among ſuch, it could not be hard for ſome of the Agents of King <hi>James</hi> to creep in.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172724:17"/>
            <p>But as when men do not cloſely and fully follow the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Conduct, if they be but a little deſerted by it, and left to themſelves, they are immediately expoſed to vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous miſcarriages; ſo there was <hi>another miſcarriage of his Anceſtors,</hi> into whibh he likewiſe fell, if what is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed and believed is true, which proved a great inlet unto all ſorts, and the very worſt of men, into Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Employments, and that was permitting the <hi>Sale of Offices and Places;</hi> or granting them at the ſollicitation of ſuch as did it for money; and which is worſe yet, ſuch as were ſtrangers, and utterly unacquainted with Perſons and their Qualities. This could not but expoſe very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Places to the Agents, not only of King <hi>James,</hi> but of the <hi>French</hi> King, to be purchaſed with his money (which of late is become more common here than ever) no dout but for his own advantage. He is believed to have been a good Chapman to thoſe who were before in places to do him but ſome particular ſervice; and therefore to get in ſuch as were intirely at his ſervice, he would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be much more liberal; but eſpecially under ſuch a juncture of affairs, when the Purchaſe of our Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in <hi>Ireland</hi> but for this laſt Summer, was worth for ought I know as much as half his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Now from ſuch people as by theſe means might be, and undoubtedly were, let into places of great importance, what can be expected leſs than all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs</hi> and <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery</hi> imaginable? and what leſs from that, than ſuch Succeſs and <hi>Diſappointments</hi> as we have met with? And what is a more natural product of that, eſpecially when it proceeds either immediately or originally from a mans own overſight or miſcarriage, than Diſhonour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt? or a juſter provocation of the Divine Majeſty to cauſe or permit it to befal them, than their neglect of his Honour and Service? <hi>He poureth Contempt upon Princes, and weakeneth the ſtrength of the Mighty,</hi> Job 12.21. Pſal. 107.40. <hi>They that honour me I will honour, but they that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172724:18"/>deſpiſe me ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. So eaſily can the moſt Wiſe and Powerful God, when he pleaſeth, cauſe a juſt puniſhment in all circumſtances of Mens Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages to proceed even naturally from ſome ſmall inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible beginning in their own actions. <hi>Thine own wickedneſs ſhall correct thee, and thy backſlidings ſhall reprove thee: Know therefore and ſee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p>And yet to give ſome gentle admonitions, that there was more than meerly natural in it, he was pleaſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termix ſome occurrences of a <hi>diſtinguiſhing Previdence.</hi> Such was that brave, undaunted, and admirably ſucceſsful Reſiſtance of all the Aſſaults of King <hi>James</hi> his Force in a cloſe Siege, for near Twelve Weeks together, by thoſe poor unexperienced and undiſciplined, but ſober and ſerious people of <hi>London-Derry:</hi> Such the magnanimous and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Attacks of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces by thoſe of <hi>Inniskiling:</hi> Whereas the Famous General <hi>Schomberg,</hi> with all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplin'd Forces of the old Army, and his experienc'd and lately ſucceſsful Forreign Forces, had not the power to hurt or attack the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, which lay encamped ſo long together almoſt by his ſide: And ſuch was that in <hi>Scotland,</hi> when one ſingle new-raiſed Regiment bore the brunt, and defeated the ſame Force which before had beaten the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral there with ſeveral Regiments of the old Army.</p>
            <p>And it is very obſervable to this purpoſe, <hi>how little ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable</hi> either to King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or to King <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> thoſe poor creatures of <hi>that diſſolute Army have been;</hi> whoſe provoking ſins, by a generous mixture of Authority, and Encouragement to reform, might have been reſtrained at firſt, and in a great meaſure cured, to the Honour of God, and greater Service in this Cauſe? But on the contrary, many of them there, languiſhing in their Iniquities, and Corporal Sickneſs together, have only helped to conſume our Proviſions, and are daily conſumed by Death, and ſwallowed up of the Earth; the Merciful God being conſtrained to purge the Land by degrees by his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172724:18"/>methods, while inconſiderate men neglect to be the Inſtruments of his milder. A pitiful and deplorable Caſe indeed; which I cannot think on without ſad Reflections upon him to whom this matter was ſo early recommended, with no inconſiderable, though very plain admonitions relating to his Station.</p>
            <p>And I do the rather take notice of this here, becauſe this <hi>Perſon</hi> was, of all Men, <hi>next to the Prince himſelf, concerned</hi> in this matter, in regard as well of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he then was in, as of that ſpecial Recommendation of a matter of ſo great conſequence to his care. Whoever was the Perſon by whom it was recommended, it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly by the ſecret direction of the ſame Providence which directed his Admonitions, and no leſs obliged him, than thoſe did them to whom they were delivered. If he did faithfully diſcharge the Duty of his Circumſtances as he ought, he hath the leſs to anſwer for: but then that is an unhappy Ingredient in this caſe. But if he did not, but inſtead of the perſonal, plain and powerful Admonitions and Perſwaſions of a judicious and faithful Divine, he took up with the prudential Conſiderations of a Stateſman or Politician; and inſtead of imminding the Prince of his great Duty of attendance to the Conduct of that power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Providence which attended him, and of exciting him to a magnanimous proſecution of that glorious work to which it led him; he prudentially miſled him to ſtop at the Bait which lay in his way, and <hi>daubing,</hi> even ſtoop to raiſe ſuch as oppos'd him, and by compliance, animate a mungrel Party; he diſabled the Prince by lowering his Authority, hath unhappily retarded, if not deſeated a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the Glorious Work which God had laid before us, and muſt be <hi>accountable both to God and Man for all the Good he might have done, and did not,</hi> and for all the Evil which hath followed upon this neglect; and the more, becauſe contrary to his own Admonitions.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:172724:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>True Divinity</hi> is much different from the Notional, Schiſmatical and Polemick, in which a man may be very ready, and have beſides a great furniture of other Reading, Oratory, and all kind of Polite Learning, as they call it, enough to make him look big, and be admired in the World, and yet be very unskilful in the other. It is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom, a quick Underſtanding in the Fear of the Lord, not to be learned in Schools, but taught of God, a Divine Ray caſt into, and kindly received in a well purified Soul; which gives it a clear, diſtinct Sight, and true Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of the different value and worth of things; an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of what is really Evil, a Contempt of what is ſplendid and gaudy, but empty and vain, the Pomps and Vanities of the World; and a juſt Eſteem of all that is really Good, according to their different degrees: of God above all, and therefore with a great care and concern for his Honour and Service; of the bleſſed Creatures above us, that they may be gratified, and not grieved or offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and of the Souls of Men, that they may be reſcued from Perdition; but of the Temporal Concerns of Men, as they are ſubſervient to this: directs it to act as a Child of Light, diſcerning what is acceptable to the Lord, and what is diſpleaſing to him. It is not to be <hi>attained</hi> by Men, whoſe affections are intaglned in the things of the World, nor conſtantly enjoyed by ſuch as are immerſed in the buſineſs of it: and yet without it, no man, let his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Parts, his acquired Accompliſhments, his Degree in Holy Orders, and his Preferments in the Church be what they will, can be <hi>a true Divine;</hi> but is in truth ſo much the greater Impoſtor, appearing in Habit and External Form what he really is not; a carnal, ſenſual or animal man at the beſt, not having the good Spirit, but in many things obnoxious to the Impreſſions and Deceits of the ſubtle Evil one; and therefore moſt dangerous to Princes and Perſons concerned in the great Affairs of the World, to be relied on. But this I intend only for a general Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172724:19"/>not to reflect upon any particular perſon, much leſs upon him before mentioned: for I do not know how he may have behaved himſelf.</p>
            <p>But of <hi>thoſe about the King,</hi> they who have been acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this Summer's ill Succeſs, eſpecially by evil Counſels, or Recommendations of evil Men, may be beſt known to himſelf. It is true, at his firſt coming he was under a great diſadvantage, that he had not ſo full knowledge of perſons as was neceſſary for the State of his Affairs: but ſuch hath been the buſineſs which ſince hath been in agitation, as cannot but have given him a competent Experimental Knowledge of thoſe who have been concerned in the moſt important parts thereof. If he do but conſider the Succeſs of his Affairs, and then recollect by whom, and whoſe Counſel or Recommendation they were managed, he may in a good meaſure perceive the Diſpoſition of the perſons, and what they deſigned or aimed at.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>the Parliament</hi> I have already mentioned ſome things with reſpect to the unſucceſsful and retarded courſe of our Proceedings: We are now enquiring into the Original and firſt Cauſe of this great Change, which is not to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the King only: The Parliament alſo have been Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals in it, and that by great and notorious defects of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Gratitude and Piety towards God; and of Juſtice, Charity, Providence, and Unanimity and Courage for their Country. They are the Repreſentative Body of the Nation: To them it belonged to have well conſidered the admirable Mercy and Favour of God in our late Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and to have made return of real Gratitude, and not put off that with a ſuperficial Formality; to have well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the defiled and ſinful State of the Nation, as well as the State of its Affairs, and to have endeavoured the Recovery of the Favour and Bleſſing of God upon thoſe, by an eſſectual Purgation and Reformation of that; and to have begun with ſome good Orders for correction of the Profaneneſs and diſſolute Manners of their own Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172724:20"/>which had been an Act of Charity and Providence for the good of their Country and of themſelves, as well as of Religion and Gratitude to God. For his Bleſſing is not to be expected upon their Conſultations now, till the Impieties and Wickedneſs of their own Members be reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or removed. And to them it belonged alſo to have made ſome Examples by Juſtice upon the Betrayers of the Rights of their Country, as well to aſſert the Juſtice of their own Proceedings againſt the late King, as to prevent encouragement to the like Practices for the future by their Connivance. And to them it belonged to have made a timely Enquiry into the Miſmanagement of Affairs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Miniſters, Counſellors, Officers, or by the King himſelf; and to have plainly, that is, faithfully repreſented the ſame to the King, and deſired Redreſs of what had been done amiſs by himſelf, and proceeded againſt the reſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſert. This was their Duty: This had been like a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament: And this doing, we might have expected God's Bleſſing: For he favours not the Wicked nor Fools, who mind not their own buſineſs. But ſuch a Puſillanimity and Baſeneſs has poſſeſſed our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments of late, ſince the diſſolute Manners were ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couroged by <hi>Ch.</hi> II. that they have been more apt to complement away the Rights of their Country, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Humour of the King, and the Safety and Honour of the King himſelf, to pleaſe his Minions and Favourites, than do any honeſt, faithful and generous Act for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and real benefit of either.</p>
            <p>Before I quite leave the Parliament it may be fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who make a part thereof, and in this caſe deſerve a ſpecial Conſideration. They are the Chief Governours of this Church: To them it belongs by their Office to take care of the Manners of the People, to be concerned at great, common and notorious National Sins, to admoniſh and importune the Civil Magiſtrate; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moreover Members of Parliament, to propoſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172724:20"/>good Laws, for the Correction and Reformation thereof. And all matters of Religion do ſo peculiarly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to their Care, that the Neglects before mentioned in the King and in the Parliament, are with no leſs Reaſon, but rather more eſpecially chargeable upon them. And it is an ill ſign of the great prevalence of Impiety and Wickedneſs in the State or Parliament it ſelf, if they durſt not, or of <hi>Laodicean</hi> Coldneſs and inſenſibility in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they would not; for certain it is they did not do in their ſtation in the Houſe, what ſo ſingular a Mercy of God, the ſo ſinful State of the Nation, this late great Change we have ſuffered in the courſe of our Affairs, and the preſent cloudy Face of things do ſo plainly require. Such a Neglect at ſuch a time as this, may juſtly move us to reflect upon former times, and the many and great Advantages, Opportunities, Occaſions and Provocations they have long had to do Good both at home and abroad; and conſidering notwithſtanding how little hath been done, to ſuſpect that <hi>Conſtantiue</hi>'s Poyſon hath ſome Lethargick or Narcotick Vertue in it to benum the Nerves, and ſtupifie the Spirits and Life of Zeal and Devotion in ſuch as taſte but a little too deep of it. And of this, to what is already mentioned, I will add Two <hi>freſh Inſtances</hi> of my own knowledge: the one of <hi>a great Clergy-man,</hi> who having well providod for himſelf in the World before elſewhere, and beſides gotten good Preferment here, could yet permit, though admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd of it, the Propagation of Religion among his own Countreymen to go a begging here for ſo ſmall a Relief and Aſſiſtance as he himſelf might very well have ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The other of <hi>ſome Dignified Perſons</hi> of conſiderable Note in the Church, who when a well affected Lay-man out of pity to Forty or Fifty Thouſand Souls, had conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and propoſed to have the Care of ſo great a Pariſh committed to ſome man of a Primitive Chriſtian Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who contenting himſelf with a reaſonable ſhare of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172724:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:172724:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172724:22"/>the Profits, would have diſtributed the reſt among as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny young Curates as it would maintain, whereby both the needs of the people might have been better ſupplied, and thoſe Perſons by their mutual advices and aſſiſtance in ſuch a Work, the better fitted and prepared for the Cure of Souls in Pariſhes of their own, yet were pleaſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe for the Preſentation, and ſo far as to obtain it at leaſt from another Competitor in no commendable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for one who had at that time a good Parſonage, a good Lecture, and a good Prebend, as a Preferment for him.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Scuffling for Preferments in the Church</hi> is a great Scandal to many ingenious Lay-Spectators, to ſuſpect the Sincerity of thoſe who take upon them to be Preachers of the Goſpel, and yet diſcover ſo little of the Power and Effects thereof in their own Actions. And this cannot but greatly obſtruct the good effect of all their Preaching upon ſuch. It is alſo a great Temptation to one of the greateſt and moſt common immediate cauſes of moſt of our Miſchieſs, both publick and private, Over-valuation and Greedineſs of the Superſluities of the things of this World, which all their Preaching can never cure, while it is daily confirmed and heightned, by ſuch Examples. And from the ſame root doth proceed all that Pharizaical Zeal for the Church, and Jealouſie and Dread of the leaſt alteration, though never ſo reaſonable and neceſſary, in many, who ſhew little ſenſe of Religion in any thing elſe, which hath long diſturbed both Church and State, and doth at this time expoſe both to danger. Theſe things being obſerved, together with ſo great coldneſs in the weighty matters of the Law, cannot but cool the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their beſt friends to them; and avert the favour both of God and Man from them. This therefore we may reaſonably look upon as one of the Original and Provoking Cauſes of this Stop and Change of the late Happy courſe of Affairs. <hi>Thou ſayeſt I am rich and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172724:22"/>with Goods, and have need of nothing; and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, and miſerable, and poor, and blind? Be zealous therefore and repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>our Judges</hi> and <hi>Civil Magiſtrates</hi> I have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to ſay: Our Courts of Juſtice are ſo well filled with ſuch Perſons, as the Profeſſion of the Law doth not afford better than moſt of them are; only few of thoſe who are in were more worthily preferred, than one, whom I need not name, was unworthily left out. His perſonal Worth doth well qualifie him for that Service; and his ſingular Merit, in his generous appearing for the Service of his Country, in occaſions of greateſt difficulty, did moſt juſtly claim it: and however it came to paſs, certainly no man of Vertue and Ingenuity would ever oppoſe it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe Corruption and Abuſes in great Places, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other miſchiefs are of pernicious conſequence by their Example, I think fit to take notice of one which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Correction, becauſe it not only concerns divers great Lords, but is obſtinately perſiſted in contrary to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Advice of Mr. <hi>Atturney</hi> himſelf. And if the Lords will paſs by ſuch an abuſe to themſelves, I know not what people of inferiour Quality may expect in time. It is the needleſs and illegal Charge they are put to, before they can be inſerted into the Commiſſion of the Peace of any County for <hi>Cuſtos Protulorum.</hi> I need but name it.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Army and Navy,</hi> the Seamen are generally honeſt, and true to their Country and the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and many among them ſober and ſerious people; but a great part of their Officers, and the Land Army, who were nearer the influence of the evil Examples at the Court, are generally ſo diſſolute and debauched, that it is not to be believed that God will ever be with them, or proſper them, but rather by degrees waſte and conſume them, till he has wholly purged the Land of them; and therefore ſo unhappy a Company of people amongſt us, muſt needs make us unproſperous and unſucceſsful, till they be either deſtroyed or reformed.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>the Body of the People of England,</hi> though
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172724:23"/>the unhappy effects of the pernicious Examples at Court have reach'd all Ranks and Degrees amongſt us, yet have they been moſt prevalent upon ſuch as were nearer in degree or converſe to it; ſo that the lower Ranks of men, which are moſt numerous, and the ſtrength of the Nation, though not wholly eſcaped, have yet been leaſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them; and were but the Examples of Vertue in our great men now, but any way proportionable to what their Examples of Vice have been for ſo long paſt, I do not doubt but they would ſoon appear again as conſiderable as heretofore they have done. So that there is little to be noted in them, but what is derived from thoſe above them, and is plainly to be imputed, not more to their neglect of good Examples, good Laws, and good Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than to the energy of their wicked, profane, and impious Examples. And theſe being beſides only Paſſive, and concerned only in the Succeſs, not in the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Affairs, are not ſo much to be conſidered in the caſe. Nor ſhall I ſay any thing of our Confederates beyond Sea. And therefore to draw up the concluſion</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>AS almoſt all the Wickedneſs of the former Reigns pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded originally from thoſe Kings, and Judgment hath been begun firſt to be executed upon them; ſo hath likewiſe the Fault, whereby that great Work, whereof this King was called out to be the Glorious Inſtrument in theſe Nations, hath been hitherto interrupted, plainly proceeded from himſelf. For by Neglect, through prudential Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance, of the Duty to which he was led, and through po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Compliance, of the Authority to which he was raiſed, by ſo manifeſt a Divine Conduct, he did not ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to himſelf, as animate againſt his Intereſt, that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which firſt oppoſed his aſcent to the Throne, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward by pernicious Counſels, and under-hand Dealings, as is believed, impoſed upon him, diſappointed his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, weakened his Reputation, and intangled him in their Snares; which yet, had he ſteadily followed the Divine Conduct, muſt have ſtooped, and quietly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:172724:23"/>
               <p>And now if we look forward, there are but <hi>two ways</hi> before him, one plain and direct, the other devious, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, full of precipices and certain miſchiefs; <hi>Via Lucis, &amp; Via Tenebrarum;</hi> the Right Way, which he left; and this which he hath unhappily choſen, wherein if he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, he is like to fall into one of theſe <hi>Inconveniencies:</hi> Either to be dangerouſly undermined by K. <hi>James</hi> his Party, of which are many of the Faction before mentioned, tho they have ſworn Fidelity to him; or elſe to be irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably engaged with the old Inſtruments of Arbitrarineſs, who conſidering how ill they have deſerved of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, can think of no better expedient to cover their own former illegal Projects, then drawing the preſent King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a participation with themſelves in the like.</p>
               <p>The <hi>natural tendency</hi> of this Way to thoſe ends, is very apparent upon a humane conſideration; and if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it with reſpect to the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> as we have great reaſon to expect upon the conſiderations before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, ſome Divine Judgment upon it, ſo none can be more agreeable to the Divine Methods in ſuch a caſe, than one of thoſe I have now mentioned, that is, either to give him up to thoſe <hi>Rehoboam</hi>-Counſels, which have been ſo pernicious to his Predeceſſors in this Throne; or to permit things to be brought to an <hi>aequilibrium</hi> between the two Princes; and by the one way, or other, put an end to that Family and Government, which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the methods, which have been uſed to reduce them to a ſence of their Duty, do ſtill continue ſo unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitable to his Service, as ſome of them have before been Obſtacles and pernicious Adverſaries to it, which yet ſtands undiſcharged upon account againſt their Succeſſors.</p>
               <p>But I hope and doubt not but <hi>the other direct and ſafe way</hi> is ſtill open for him to return unto, only being now ſomewhat more difficult, it will require, and deſervedly, ſo much the greater Reſolution. And this I take to be the way: Firſt, to be careful to uſe all approv'd means for the <hi>Recovery af the Divine Favour;</hi> and then to apply to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172724:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>uſe of ſuch <hi>Humane Means,</hi> as true Wiſdom and ſolid Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy direct and require. But it muſt be in this Order, or elſe he will never recover the like proſperous Succeſs; but whatever alterations in Miniſters or Politicks he ſhall make without that, will either prove unſucceſsful, or prove ſo to him, he ſhall have but little enjoyment of it.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Recovery of the Divine Favour</hi> in this caſe it will be abſolutely neceſſary,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſettle, by good conſideration of the many expreſs Declarations and parallel Examples in the Sa. Scripture, a <hi>right and firm Judgment;</hi> 1. That whatever were the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate apparent Cauſes of the former happy Succeſs, and of the ill ſucceſs ſince, yet that the Principal, hegemonical Cauſe in both was from God. 2. That the Provoking Cauſe of this great Change muſt have been no ſmall Sin. 3. That there can be no hope of recovery of the Divine Favour and former Proſperous Condition, but by effectual remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of that Sin, whatever it be. 4. That of all the Sins, which have been noted for the greateſt Provocations of the like Judgements heretofore, there are none ſo likely to have had ſuch unhappy effect in this caſe at that which is ſo often expreſſed in the Sacred Scripture by the phraſe of the <hi>Heart</hi> being <hi>lifted up,</hi> with its conſequence of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God. As in thoſe great Cautions <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.14. &amp; 17.10. and in thoſe remarkable Examples, even of <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 32.25. that <hi>he rendred not again</hi> to the Lord <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Benefit done unto him: for his Heart was lifted up; therefore there was Wrath upon him, and upon Juda and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> And of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 26.16. <hi>When he was ſtrong, his heart was lifted up to his deſtruction.</hi> and Deſertion or Neglect of the Special Work wherein one is employed; of which <hi>Saul</hi> is a remarkable Example. Laſtly, that there can be no removal of theſe Sins without great Humiliation upon contemplation of the Ingratitude, and dangerous conſequence thereof, and a Reſolute Return to the deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or neglected Duty, and therefore</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:172724:24"/>
               <p n="2">2. To ſet reſolvedly to the Work of an <hi>Effectual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> of this People, whom God hath ſubjected to him, and committed to his Charge, to be delivered from the Slavery of their Souls to Satan by impudent Sins, as well as of their Perſons and Eſtates to Tyrants by Uſurpation; Which may by the ſame Divine Favour, which will not then be wanting to his own Work, be eaſily effected. 1. By a plain <hi>Declaration</hi> of his Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, commanding a ſtrict Execution of the Laws in force for that purpoſe. Which is one great part of the Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Office. 2. By a ſteady uſe of his own <hi>immediate Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> excluding and rejecting from his Counſels, Service and Preſence, all ſuch as obſtinately refuſe Obedience and Conformity to ſo juſt, reaſonable and neceſſary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and Reſolutions. And this muſt be done, not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficially, but with great Reſolution and Conſtancy, and the greater by reaſon of the Failure before committed; even to the hazard of his Kingdom (if there was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) for his ſake, who hath raiſed him to the Throne, and can when he pleaſeth, as ſoon remove him from it, and lay him and his Honour in the Duſt. Such a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution once declared will half do the Work: But it muſt be ſteadily purſued, and impartial, without Indulgence to any: for that would be to prefer a Creature before the Creator, and would prove very pernicious. Beſides, ſuch Fools and Mad-men, as are profane, or glory in their Shame; and ſuch impotent Bruits, as have not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of themſelves to abſtain from ſcandalous Sins, are not fit to be admittend into the Service or Favour of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and generous Prince. 3. By <hi>paſſing</hi> and even <hi>recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending</hi> ſuch other <hi>good Laws,</hi> as are neceſſary for ſupply of the Defects of thoſe we have already. This is the way to recover God's Bleſſing: and this will ſtrengthen him with the Hearts and Hands of the beſt and moſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of the Nation. And this being done, he may with Confidence, and without Delay, proceed to</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:172724:25"/>
               <p n="2">2. The Proper <hi>Human Means;</hi> and 1. Such as are, and always will be, neceſſary <hi>to ſtrengthen his Kingdom at home</hi> in the Hearts of the People. Which is to be done by good Government, and avoiding thoſe known Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences into which his late Predeceſſors of this Age ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily fell. But more particularly, 1. By <hi>Juſtice,</hi> (a great part of that Righteouſneſs, by which the Throne is eſtabliſhed,) both to the Community, and to each Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual, without Uſurpation, Encroachments, or Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either by himſelf, or his Favourites, or Officers. 2. By <hi>Faithfulneſs in the Diſcharge of the Regal Office,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting all his Counſels and Actions for the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Nation, as his End, and according to the true Conſtitution of the State and Government, as his Rule This is plainly his Duty, and that, for which, and with which, he is intruſted as King, as is very appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in all the parts of the Conſtitution, let Sycophants and Flatterers ſay what they can to the contrary. And to this purpoſe <hi>three great Faults of the late Reigns</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to be avoided: 1. The Uſe of any <hi>ſingle Miniſtry</hi> of Favourites, or <hi>Private Adviſers</hi> in Cabals; ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be done but by Advice of a Legal well-choſen <hi>Privy Council,</hi> and under the Hands of thoſe who adviſe it. 2. As well the long <hi>Continuance,</hi> as long <hi>Intermiſſion</hi> of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> which are both equally inconſiſtent with the Statutes in force for Annual Parliaments; and of equally pernicious Conſequence. 3. The <hi>Corruption of Members of Parliament</hi> by Penſions, Places, and Promiſes; which is ſuch a Breech of Truſt on both ſides, as is odious both to God and Man, and equal to what in private matter is commonly reputed the baſeſt Knavery that can be.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>Prudence and Induſtry</hi> in ordering all, as to this End, and by this Rule, ſo for the beſt Advantage upon all occaſions; As, 1. In the choice of fit Perſons for Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. 2. In Inſpection into their Behaviour. 3. In provident Management of the Revenue and Contribution,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172724:25"/>that no unneceſſary charge be laid upon the People. 4. In conferring of Honours, wherein great faults have been committed in the late Reigns. And in many other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars not neceſſary here to be expreſſed.</p>
               <p>By theſe means he may make both himſelf and theſe Kingdoms happy. For it is certain, unleſs I have been long in a great miſtake, that both the true Conſtitution of this State and Government is as well compoſed, both for Prince and People, as any in the World; and the People as well diſpoſed to be happily and eaſily governed by it, as any upon the face of the Earth, by any Government whatever. But it was the unhappineſs of the laſt Race of Kings to be ſo impoſed upon by Flatterers, that they never well underſtood either; or were carried away contrary to their own ſenſe or reaſon, as they plainly were in many things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But beſides theſe things which are of conſtant uſe to be obſerved at all times, there may be ſome <hi>things now ſpecially requiſite,</hi> or adviſable for the preſent State of Affairs: And ſuch among others, I humbly conceive may be,</p>
               <p n="1">1. A fair <hi>Diſmiſſion</hi> for the preſent, till things be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſetled, both from the Privy Council, and from the Management of Affairs relating to <hi>Ireland, of all ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> as either he himſelf hath known to be unhappy in their Counſels to himſelf; or are commonly believed by others to have been concerned in any illegal Practices, or Projects in the late Reigns; or have incurred the ill Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the preſent Parliament: And to make choice of ſuch other underſtanding Men of unſpotted Integrity, though of inferiour Quality, as are leaſt ſuſpected of Partiality to any Faction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A <hi>Diſſolution of the preſent Parliament,</hi> and new Writs to be ſpeedily ſent out to ſummon another to ſit at as ſhort a day as may be; to confirm the Acts of this, and to put an end to all doubts concerning the Authority of it.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:172724:26"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Execution of Juſtice</hi> upon the Diſturbers of the preſent Settlement.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Review of thoſe Counſels and Proceedings which have given ſuch diſturbance in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and a ſpeedy Reſtitution of matters there, to the true Conſtitution of that Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A juſt Inſpection into the <hi>Accounts</hi> of all the Money before given, and a good <hi>Management</hi> of the Remainder of that, and of this lately given, for ſpeedy <hi>Preparation</hi> for the next Spring, to recover, if poſſible, the Reputation and Advantages loſt the laſt Summer.</p>
               <p>The Life of Man is ſhort and incertain; of Kings more incertain, but of this King, by reaſon of his corporal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, moſt of all. He hath therefore cauſe to be the more provident in the Management of the Opportunities and great Talents, with which he is intruſted both by God and Man; and of which he muſt ſhortly give account, ſo as that he may do it with Joy, and not with Grief. Every wiſe man will make it his chief care to direct all his Actions to the attainment of his greateſt perſonal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and of his Enjoyment of the moſt excellent Being. The ſame ought to be the care of thoſe who have any Power over others, to help them as much as may be to do the like. And this is more eſpecially the part of a Wiſe and Good King; and the ready way to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and the People under him, happy here, as well as hereafter. It will make him King of Men, of more than Men, that is, Chriſtians; not of Brutes and Devils: and of a whole Nation, not only of a Party or Faction. And for this, no labour ought to be ſpared, no Difficulties or Dangers feared; otherwiſe King <hi>James</hi> will riſe in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condemn Him.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
